A Preliminary Inventory of the Bronis J. Kaslas papers, 1899-1974
Hoover Institution Archives
Bronis J. Kaslas papers, 1899-1974
76116
Kaslas, Bronis J., 1910-1996
4 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize box (2 linear feet)
The papers consist of writings and rare printed matter relating to Eastern European politics, the Russian occupation of Lithuania, Lithuanians in foreign countries, the Baltic States, Poland, and the Paris Peace Conference of 1946.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1976.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
A Lithuanian-American historian, Kaslas was the author of several books including The Lithuanian Strip in Soviet-German Secret Diplomacy, 1939-1941 and The USSR-German Aggression against Lithuania.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers consist of writings and rare printed matter relating to Eastern European politics, the Russian occupation of Lithuania, Lithuanians in foreign countries, the Baltic States, Poland, and the Paris Peace Conference of 1946.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Lithuania--Emigration and immigration.; World War, 1939-1945--Lithuania.; World War, 1939-1945--Peace.; Baltic States--History.; Europe, Eastern--Politics and government.; Lithuania--History.; Lithuania--History--Soviet occupation, 1940-1941.; Lithuania--Social conditions.; Poland--History.
Collection Contents
- Die Vernichtung des Osteuropas, 1949-1950 and 1954
  - Typescript with corrections, 1954 (Folder 1: 1-3)
  - Typescript, 1949-1950 (Folder 1: 4-5)
- Liste des Journalistes accrédités auprès de la Conférence de Paris arrêtés le 15 Août 1946, C.P. Presse no. 51 (Folder 1: 6)
- Discours de S.E. le Ministre des Affaires Etrangères de Hollande, Conférence de Paris, C.P. Presse 11, 1946 (Folder 1: 7)
- Liste des Dèlègations, Conférence de Paris, C.P. Presse, 1946 July 30 (Folder 1: 8)
- Die Sowjetisierung Osteuropas, typescript, 1958 (Folder 2: 1-2)
- Nykstante uke, manuscript, 1899 (Folder 2: 3)
- Untitled manuscript on Poland, in English, undated (Folder 2: 4-5)
- Das Schicksal Osteuropas, typescript with corrections, 1950s (Folder 2: 6-7)
- Gesetze, Anordnungen und Verordnungen: die Rechtspflege die in Litauen zur Zeit der bolschewistischen Okkupation erlassen worden sind, 1950s
  - Erste Abteilung: Die Justiz, 1950s (Folder 2: 8)
    - Das Zentrale Organ der Justiz zur Zeit der bolschewisitischen Gewaltherrschaft, 1950s (Folder 2: 9)
  - Zweite Abteilung: Das Strafrecht, 1950s (Folder 2: 10)
  - Dritte Abteilung: Das Privatrecht, 1950s (Folder 2: 11)
  - Vierte Abteilung: Das Recht, die Ehe, die Familie und die Vormundschaft, 1950s (Folder 2: 12)
- Research materials on the diplomatic history of the Baltic States from 1918 to 1945, in English, 1950s (Folder 3: 1-6)
- The USSR-German Aggression against Lithuania, manuscript and research materials, 1960s-1970s (Folder 4: 1-12)
- Collected reports and articles from the American Academy of Political and Social Sciences 78th Annual meeting, "USA-USSR: Agenda for Communication," Philadelphia, 1974 (Folder 4: 13-15)
- Vepla: Dvisavaitinis Satyros Žurnalas, 1928 January (Folder 5)